Some 17 years ago, I became allergic to Delhi's air.
منذ ما يقرب عن 17 عام، أصبحت لدي حساسية من هواء دلهي
My doctors told me that my lung capacity
قال لي أطبائي أن قدرة رئتي
had gone down to 70 percent,
إنخفضت إلى 70 في المائة
and it was killing me.
وأنها تقتلني
With the help of IIT,
يمساعدة عدة معاهد
TERI, and learnings from NASA,
وبعض الفوائد من ناسا
we discovered that there are three
أكتشفنا أن هناك ثلاث
basic green plants,
نباتات خضراء أساسية
common green plants, with which
نباتات خضراء شائعة، وبها
we can grow all the fresh air
يمكننا إنبات كل الهواء النقي
we need indoors to keep us healthy.
الذي نحتاجه في المنزل لنبقى أصحاء
We've also found that you can
ووجدنا أيضا أنه يمكنك
reduce the fresh air requirements
خفض متطلبات الهواء النقي
into the building, while maintaining
إلى داخل المبنى، بينما نحافظ
industry indoor air-quality standards.
على جودة عالية للهواء
The three plants are Areca palm,
الثلاث نباتات هي نخلة الأريقة
Mother-in-Law's Tongue and money plant.
لسان الحما ونبتة المال
The botanical names are in front of you.
الأسماء النباتية أمامكم
Areca palm is a plant which
الأريقة هي النبات الذي
removes CO2 and converts it into oxygen.
يسحب ثاني أكسيد الكربون ويحوله إلى أكسيجين
We need four shoulder-high plants per person,
نجتاج إلى أربع نبتات بإرتفاع الكتف لكل شخص
and in terms of plant care,
ومن حيث رعاية النباتات
we need to wipe the leaves
نحتاج إلى مسح الأوراق
every day in Delhi, and perhaps
كل يوم في دلهي، وربما
once a week in cleaner-air cities.
مرة كل أسبوع في مدن أنظف هواءا
We had to grow them in vermi manure,
كان علينا تربيتها في السماد
which is sterile, or hydroponics,
والذي كان معقما
and take them outdoors every three to four months.
ونأخذه للخارج كل ثلاثة إلى أربع أشهر
The second plant is Mother-in-law's Tongue,
النبتة الثانية هي لسان الحما
which is again a very common plant,
وهو نبات شائع آخر
and we call it a bedroom plant,
ونسميه نبات غرفة النوم
because it converts CO2 into oxygen at night.
لأنه يحول ثاني أكسيد الكربون إلى الأكسجين في الليل
And we need six to eight waist-high plants per person.
ونحتاج إلى ست إلى سبع نبتات بإرتفاع الخصر لكل شخص
The third plant is money plant,
النبتة الثالثة هي نبتة المال
and this is again a very common plant;
وهذا أيضا نبات شائع جدا
preferably grows in hydroponics.
يفضل أن ينمو في الماء
And this particular plant removes formaldehydes
هذا النبات تحديدا يزيل الفورمالدهيد
and other volatile chemicals.
وغيرها من المواد الكيميائية الضارة
With these three plants,
بهذه النبتات الثلاث
you can grow all the fresh air you need.
يمكنكم إنبات كل الهواء النقي الذي تحتاجونه
In fact, you could be in a bottle
في الواقع، يمكن أن تكون في زجاجة
with a cap on top, and you would not die at all,
مغلقة، ولن تموت
and you would not need any fresh air.
ولن تحتاج إلى أي هواء نقي
We have tried these plants at our
لقد جربنا هذخ النباتات في
own building in Delhi, which is a
مبنانا في دلهي، وهو
50,000-square-feet, 20-year-old building.
يمساحة 50,000 قدم، وعمره 20 عام
And it has close to 1,200 such plants for 300 occupants.
به ما يقرب من 1,200 نبات و 300 ساكن
Our studies have found that there is
أوضحت دراساتنا أن هناك
a 42 percent probability of one's blood oxygen
إحتمال 42 أن تزداد نسبة الأكسجين في الدم
going up by one percent if one stays indoors
بنسبة واحد في المائة إذا بقي الشخص في
in this building for 10 hours.
هذا المبنى لعشر ساعات
The government of India has discovered
إكتشفت حكومة الهند
or published a study to show
أو نشرت دراسة تظهر
that this is the healthiest building in New Delhi.
أن هذا هو أصح مبنى في نيو دلهي
And the study showed that,
وأوضحت الدراسة أن هناك
compared to other buildings,
مقارنة بالمباني الباقية
there is a reduced incidence of
هناك إنخفاض في حالات
eye irritation by 52 percent,
تهيج العين بنسبة 52 في المائة
respiratory systems by 34 percent,
نظم الجهاز التنفسي بنسبة 34 في المائة
headaches by 24 percent,
الصداع بنسبة 24 في المائة
lung impairment by 12 percent and asthma by nine percent.
إصابة الرئة بنسبة 12 في المئة والربو بنسبة 9 فى المائة
And this study has been published on September 8, 2008,
وقد نشرت هذه الدراسة في 8 سبتمبر 2008
and it's available on the government of India website.
وهي متاحة على موقع الحكومة الهندية
Our experience points to an
خبرتنا تشير إلى
amazing increase in human productivity
زيادة مدهشة في الإنتاج البشري
by over 20 percent by using these plants.
بأكثر من 20 في المائة بإستخدام هذه النباتات
And also a reduction in energy requirements in buildings
وكذلك إنخفاض في إحتياجات الطاقة للمبنى
by an outstanding 15 percent, because you need less fresh air.
بنسبة 15 في المائة، لأنك بحاجة إلى كمية أقل من الهواء النقي
We are now replicating this in a
ونحن الآن بصدد تكرار ذلك في
1.75-million-square-feet building,
مبنى بحجم 1.75 مليون قدم
which will have 60,000 indoor plants.
سيكون بداخله 60,000 نبات
Why is this important?
ما أهمية ذلك؟
It is also important for the environment,
إنه أيضا مهم للبيئة
because the world's energy
لأن المتوقع زيادة
requirements are expected to grow
إجتياجات الطاقة في العالم
by 30 percent in the next decade.
بنسبة 30 في المائة خلال العقد القادم
40 percent of the world's energy is taken
و 40 في المائة من طاقة العالم تستهلك
up by buildings currently,
حاليا من مباني
and 60 percent of the world's population
و 60 في المائة من سكان العالم
will be living in buildings in cities
سيسكنون في مباني في مدن
with a population of over one million in the next 15 years.
ذات تعداد ملون أو أكثر خلال 15 عام المقبلة
And there is a growing preference for living
وهناك تزايد في تفضيل السكن
and working in air-conditioned places.
والعمل في الأماكن المكيفة
"Be the change you want to see in the world,"
كن المتغير الذي تود رؤيته في العالم
said Mahatma Gandhi.
كما قال المهاتما غاندي
And thank you for listening.
وشكرا لإستماعكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)